A Guide to the Legislative Case Files of the Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, 1989-2003
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Legislative Case Files of the Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services 1988-2004
The Library of Virginia
43687
19 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Legislative Case Files, Jefferson Building, 13th Floor, 1220 Bank Street, Richmond, VA 23219, transferred 25 March 2008 and accessioned 26 March 2008.
Biographical Information
The Dept. of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services traces it beginnings to the first institution in the New World designed for the treatment of the mentally ill, which opened in Williamsburg in 1773. Now known as Eastern State Hospital, it was followed by Western State Hospital, in Staunton (1828), Central State Hospital, in Petersburg (1885), and Southwestern State Hospital, in Marion (1887). Each hospital had its own governing/management body. The first State Hospital Board was created by an act of the General Assembly passed on December 24, 1936. It replaced the individual governing boards and brought the institutions and training schools under one state agency.
On April 3, 1942, the General Assembly passed an act establishing the Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals. The name of the department was changed to the Department of Mental Health and Mental Retardation by the General Assembly on March 20, 1973. Substance abuse was added to the name March 25, 1987.
The Department is responsible for providing a comprehensive system of services that is responsive to the mental health, mental retardation, drug abuse and alcohol dependency needs of the citizens of the Commonwealth. The Department has developed many programs to fulfill its responsibilities, including treatment, counseling, hospitalization, and rehabilitation services.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services, Legislative Case Files, are housed in 19 boxes. This collection has been processed using minimal processing standards: the original arrangement has been maintained, the level of description is brief and simple, and the records have not been refoldered and fasteners have not been removed. These records include bills, correspondence, memorandums, legislative files, briefing books, photographs, negatives, and reports. These records document legislative studies, proposals and case files of the Virginia Department of Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services.
Notable materials include: extensive files related to House Joint Resolution 240 (passed by the Virginia General Assembly, 2 April 1996) which established a joint subcommittee to evaluate the future delivery of public funded mental health, mental retardation, and substance abuse services.
Contents List
- SJR 440, 2001 (Box 1 (C-31), Folder 1)
- JLARC Study, 2004 (Box 1 (C-31), Folder 2)
- OIG Study (Box 1 (C-31), Folder 3)
- Human Rights Study Group, 1997-1998 (Box 1 (C-31), Folder 4)
- "Managed Care in the Publicly Funded System of Care in Virginia," 1997 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 1)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 2)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 3)
- Presentation to the Subcommittee Studying the Publicly Funded MHMRSAS System, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 4)
- Managed Health Care Issues and Community Services for Persons with Mental Retardation, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 5)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 6)
- Mental Health System Funding and Services, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 7)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 8)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 9)
- HJR 240, 1996 (Box 2 (C-32), Folder 10)
- Photos and negatives, 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 1)
- HJR 240 (Joint Committee to Evaluate the Future Delivery of Publicly Funded Mental Health, Mental Retardation and Substance Abuse Services), 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 2)
- Presentation on the Comprehensive State Plan, (1998-2004), 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 3)
- HJR 240, 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 4)
- HJR 240, 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 5)
- HJR 240, 1997 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 6)
- Community Services Board Overview, FY1996 (Box 3 (C-33), Folder 7)
- HJR 240, 1998 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 1)
- Mental Health Workgroup Materials, 1998 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 2)
- HJR 240 Response, 1998 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 3)
- HJR 240, 1997 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 4)
- HJR 240, 1997 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 5)
- HJR 240, 1998 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 6)
- HJR 225/240, 1998 (Box 4 (C-34), Folder 7)
- HJR 225, 1999 (Box 5 (C-35), Folder 1)
- Hammond Commission, 1999 (Box 5 (C-35), Folder 2)
- House Documents, 1988 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 1)
- Senate Documents, 1988 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 2)
- Legislative Studies, 1988-1989 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 3)
- House Bill 414, 1988 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 4)
- HJR 287, Need of Head Inj., 1988 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 5)
- Annual Certification Legislation, 1989 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 6)
- Joint Subcommittee on HIV, 1988-1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 7)
- Head Injury Study, 1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 8)
- Task Force on Drug Trafficking, 1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 9)
- Appropriations/Finance, 1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 10)
- Census Management Study, 1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 11)
- Report on Community Services Initiative, 1988-1989 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 12)
- Gambling Disorders, 1990 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 13)
- Legislative Packet, 1991 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 14)
- Crime Commission and Outpatient Commitment, 1991 (Box 6 (C-36), Folder 15)
- Summary of Act, 1989 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 1)
- Senate Joint Resolution 191, 1989 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 2)
- Legislative Studies, 1989 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 3)
- Legislative Package, 1989-1990 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 4)
- Legislative Session Final Disposition, 1990 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 5)
- Legislation, 1990 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 6)
- Legislative File, 1990 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 7)
- Legislative File, 1990 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 8)
- Legislative Proposals, 1991 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 9)
- Legislative Package, 1991 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 10)
- Legislative Issues, 1991 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 11)
- Legislative Final Disposition, 1991 (Box 7 (C-37), Folder 12)
- Legislative Studies Material, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 1)
- Summary of the Acts of Assembly, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 2)
- Legislative Information, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 3)
- JLARC Information, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 4)
- Crime Commission, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 5)
- Recommendations, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 6)
- Medically Fragile Children, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 7)
- Interim Reports, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 8)
- Local Mandates Review, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 9)
- Legislative Spreadsheets, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 10)
- Commission on HC, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 11)
- CSA, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 12)
- Commission on Youth, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 13)
- Legislative Package, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 14)
- Legislative Calendar, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 15)
- Transition Package, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 16)
- Legislation Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 17)
- Final Legislation Disposition, 1993 (Box 8 (C-38), Folder 18)
- Legislative Package, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 1)
- Legislative Package, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 2)
- Legislative Package, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 3)
- Recommendations to Gov./Legislation, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 4)
- Stambough Foundation, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 5)
- HJ 180, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 6)
- HJ 182, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 7)
- HJ 247, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 8)
- Project Link, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 9)
- SJR 107, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 10)
- HJR 129, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 11)
- HJ 163, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 12)
- HJ 174, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 13)
- Legislative Correspondence, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 14)
- Legislative Package, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 15)
- Commitment of Minors, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 16)
- CSA, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 17)
- HB 1329, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 18)
- HJR 38, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 19)
- Children's Issues, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 20)
- Crime Commission Studies, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 21)
- Early Childhood and Day Care Programs (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 22)
- Essential Health Services Panel (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 23)
- Governor's Office (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 24)
- Guardianship Task Force, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 25)
- Joint Board Liaison Committee (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 26)
- Legislative Issues, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 27)
- Legislative Materials (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 28)
- Annie P. Casey Foundation, 1992 (Box 9 (C-39), Folder 29)
- Legislative Case Files, 1994 (Box 10 (C-40), Folder 1)
- Legislative Process-Drug Courts, 1994 (Box 10 (C-40), Folder 2)
- Bill Book and Reports, 1994 (Box 10 (C-40), Folder 3)
- Legislative Studies, 1994 (Box 10 (C-40), Folder 4)
- Legislative Case Files, 1994-1995 (Box 11 (C-41), Folder 1)
- Budget Initiatives, 1995 (Box 11 (C-41), Folder 2)
- Legislative Case Files (Box 11 (C-41), Folder 3)
- Legislative Case Files (Box 11 (C-41), Folder 4)
- Legislative Proposals, 1995 (Box 11 (C-41), Folder 5)
- Legislative Package, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 1)
- Budget Materials, 1994-1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 2)
- Final Disposition, Legislative Session, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 3)
- Enrolled Bill Reviews, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 4)
- Legislative Fact Sheets, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 5)
- Legislative Fact Sheets, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 6)
- Legislative Fact Sheets, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 7)
- Legislative Action Summaries, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 8)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 9)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 10)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 11)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 12)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 13)
- Legislative Case Files, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 14)
- Legislative Action Summaries, 1996 (Box 12 (C-42), Folder 15)
- Legislative Action Summaries/Budget Information, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 1)
- Legislative Case Files, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 2)
- JLARC ACR Study, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 3)
- Legislative Case Files, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 4)
- Legislative Action Summaries and Bills, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 5)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 6)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 7)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 8)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 9)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 10)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 11)
- Legislation, 1997 (Box 13 (C-43), Folder 12)
- Legislative Files, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 1)
- Senate Bills, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 2)
- Bill Book, 1999 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 3)
- Legislative Correspondence, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 4)
- Legislative Files, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 5)
- Legislative Files, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 6)
- Legislative Proposals, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 7)
- Legislative Project, 1998 (Box 14 (C-44), Folder 8)
- Legislative Files, 2000 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 1)
- Bill Book, 1999 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 2)
- Legislation, 1999 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 3)
- Joint Subcommittee on HIV, 1999 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 4)
- HJR 581, 1999 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 5)
- Enrolled Bill Reviews/Legislative Action Summaries, 1999 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 6)
- Legislative Files, 1999-2000 (Box 15 (C-45), Folder 7)
- Legislative Action Summaries/Enrolled Bill Reviews, 2000 (Box 16 (C-46), Folder 1)
- Bill Book, 2000 (Box 16 (C-46), Folder 2)
- Legislative Action Summaries/Enrolled Bill Reviews, 2001 (Box 17 (C-47), Folder 1)
- Legislative Files, 2001 (Box 17 (C-47), Folder 2)
- Legislative Proposals, 2001 (Box 17 (C-47), Folder 3)
- Bill Book, 2001 (Box 17 (C-47), Folder 4)
- Legislative Files, 2001 (Box 17 (C-47), Folder 5)
- Bill Book, 2002 (Box 18 (C-48), Folder 1)
- Legislative Files, 2002 (Box 18 (C-48), Folder 2)
- Juvenile NGRI (Not Guilty by Reason of Insanity), 2002-2003 (Box 18 (C-48), Folder 3)
- Bill Book, 2003 (Box 19 (C-49), Folder 1)
- Legislative Files, 2003 (Box 19 (C-49), Folder 2)
- Title Revision, 2003 (Box 19 (C-49), Folder 3)
- Criminal Records Check Legislation, 2003 (Box 19 (C-49), Folder 4)